Shrikant Kumar

Sr. Technical Associate
@shrikant.kumar@outllok.com
+91- 860412443, 9818051144

Executive Summary

Scaling new heights of success and leaving a mark of excellence in assignments which involve analytical capabilities and professional growth.

Technical Skills

Skill	Skill Sub Category
Java	Core Java, Spring/ Spring Boot, Hibernate, Apache Axis2, Java EE, JAX-RS, JAX-WS, Struts, Servlet, Java8, JBoss, Spring Security, WebLogic, WebServices, JMX, Tomcat, JNDI, JDBC, JSP, Grails & Groovy
Big Data	Hadoop, Hive
Databases	Oracle, MySQL, Informix, DB2
Javascript	AJAX, jQuery UI, Angular 4, Node Js
NoSQL DB	Nosql DB, MangoDB
Jira	Jira Administration
Mobile	Android SDK
Security	Data Encryption, LDAP, HTTPS and TLS/SSL
AWS	EC2, Route53, SQS/SNS, ELB, IAM, Inbound/Outbound, Security, Cloud Formation Template, Cloudwatch, Amazon MQ, Gateways, VPC, Lambda, S3, Node Autoscaling etc.
Build Tools	Gradle, Maven, Ant, Jenkins with docker and aws

Certifications

Certification Authority	Certification Name
CDAC	Post Graduate Dimploma in Software Technologies

Foreign Language Skills

Language	Written	Spoken
English	Expert	Expert

Education

Institution: Punjab Technical University

Date(s) Attended: September 2011 - April 2014

Qualification(s): MCA

Major Subject(s): Java, Computer Graphics, Compiler Design, RDBMS, Software

Engineering, Operating system, Object oriented analysis & design,

Data Structure, Visual Basic, Computer Based Optimization

Methods

Institution: Patna University

Date(s) Attended: May 2004 - July 2007

Qualification(s): BCA

Major Subject(s): Computer Fundamentals & organizations, Programming techniques,

Office automation, Business data processing, DBMS, Operating system, Data Structure, Entrepreneurship development program

Professional Experience

6. Company: Sapient Consulting Pvt. Ltd.

Duration: Feb 2018 – Present

Role: Senior Technical Associate

Project Wellington Management offers comprehensive investment management **Description:** capabilities that span nearly all segments of the global capital markets.

It only business is in investment management, to exceed the investment

objectives and service expectations for clients worldwide.

Responsibilities: Key responsibility are:

Generate Account specific report

Annually/Semi/Quarterly/Monthly

Project feasibility/environment discussion with US client.
 Processing the report and publishing it on SharePoint.

Managing document using alfresco CRM.

Implementing custom ui with alfresco for client report visibility

and sharing.

Technologies: Java 8 /OOPS, Design Pattern, Multithreading, Collection, Concurrency,

Spring & Boot, Hibernate, Amazon Web-Services, Angular 4, Node Js, Grails & Groovy, Gradle & Maven, Jenkins, Alfresco, SharePoint, Salesforce, Oracle, Maestro Job Scheduling, Bash Script...

5. Company: Global Logic India Limited **Duration:** Aug 2017 – Feb 2018

Role: Consultant

Project Ericsson TV Media:

Description: Internet Protocol television (IPTV) is the delivery of television content

over Internet Protocol (IP) networks. This is in contrast to delivery through traditional terrestrial, satellite, and cable television formats. Unlike downloaded media, IPTV offers the ability to stream the source media continuously. As a result, a client media player can begin playing

the content (such as a TV channel) almost immediately.

Although IPTV uses the Internet protocol it is not limited to television streamed from the Internet, (Internet television). IPTV is widely deployed in subscriber-based telecommunications networks with high-speed access channels into end-user premises via set-top boxes or other customer-premises equipment. IPTV is also used for media delivery around corporate and private networks. IPTV in the telecommunications arena is notable for its ongoing standardisation process (e.g., European

Telecommunications Standards Institute).

Responsibilities: Key responsibility during my tenure here are:

Requirement study

Project feasibility/environment discussion.

Finalization of technology stack to be used for this project.

Resource requirement with head counts.
 Update progress status to manager.

Technologies: Java/OOPS, Design Pattern, Multithreading, Collection, Concurrency,

Spring & Boot, Hibernate, Java 8, Web-Services, Angular 2

4. Company: **NIIT Technologies**

Duration: Nov 2016 - May 2017 (6 months)

Role: **Technical Analyst**

Project SITA is the world's leading provider of global Information Technology Description: and Telecommunications solutions to the Air Transport Industry. SITA

Voyager Program is replacing the existing mainframe based

reservations systems based on a Service Oriented Architecture (SOA)

approach with Java.

Services Offered

Airline commercial management.

Baggage processing.

Flight operations.

Ground operations.

Infrastructure & communication technologies.

Maintenance, repair and overhaul.

Passenger processing.

Sales, customer loyalty & marketing.

Responsibilities:

Key responsibilities during my tenure are:

Performance Tuning using JRMC, JMeter, Soap UI &

JProfiler/YourKit

Create millions of dummy data in DB for particular operation to perform performance tuning.

Provide solution for non-preferment code.

Prepare the SLA report for each operation

Unit Testing using Power mock & Mockito

Review Peer code and enhance it to meet the current requirement.

Create a mapping document using Contivo and Mappy.

Verify the XSD/Xml file using XmlSpy.

On daily basis participate in scrum meeting with client.

Monitoring work progress status using Jira.

Create code-coverage report using jenikins, cobertura and

Technologies:

Angular 2, Java/J2EE, OOPS, Multithreading, Concurrency, Xml Parser Jibx & Jaxp, Hibernate, Spring, Spring Boot, Junit & Mockito, Rest & Soap Web-Service, Maven, Sonar, Jenkins, Oracle DB, Web-Logic, Oracle Coherence, Oracle Service Bus, YourKit, JProfiler, Soap Ui Pro,

JRockit, Linux etc.

3. Company: Estel Technologies Pvt Ltd, Gurgaon **Duration:** Apr 2015 - Oct 2016 (over 1 year)

Role: Sr Software Engineer

Project Description: Mobile Banking application helps banks increase service penetration, enhance customer loyalty and stickiness, reduce cost of operations and increase revenue. With mobile banking, banks can empower its customers to securely access their bank accounts using their mobile phones to get information of their accounts like available balance, transactions summary etc. and also make transactions in real time. Mobile Banking facilitates banks to reach all potential customers. banked and unbanked across geographies in a very speedy and cost

effective manner.

Micro Banking platform enables inclusive and low-cost banking, remittances, mobile payments and other mobile financial services to millions of people in countries where banking services are not easily available or accessible. It enables mobile financial services for millions of unbanked customers and offers enormous potential to open new markets and business opportunities for Banks, MNOs, Money Transfer and Payment Service Providers.

Services Offered

- Cash Deposit
- Cash Withdrawal (cash out from Agent)
- Balance Check
- Mini Statement
- Prepaid / Postpaid Recharge
- Bill Payments
- Bank Fund Transfer
- Send Money
- Receive Money
- Wallet Transfer
- Wallet Topup
- Wallet Adjustment
 - Customer KYC Registration

Responsibilities:

Key responsibility during my tenure here are:

- Requirement Gathering.
- Design Module and change database schema to meet the requirement.
- Coding and code analysis using sonar.
- Unit Testing using Junit.
- Review Peer code to enhance the performance.
- Client interaction for requirement changes or gathering
- Implementation of AWS sns and sqs for push notification.
- Monitoring work progress using Jira.
- Manage the code versioning in SVN/CVS.
- Implementation of adaptor for restful services.
- Received star performance and Client satisfaction award for this project

Technologies:

Angular 2, Java/J2EE, OOPS, Multithreading, Concurrency, Hibernate, Spring, Spring boot, Junit, Restful & Soap Web-Service, Ant, Informix, Jboss As 7, Json & Jackson, IntelliJ IDEA 16, Velocity Template, Amazon Web Services, Baidu, Apple and Google Cloud Push Notification Implementation, Jira, Jenkins, Linux.

2. Company: NISG, Delhi

Duration: May 2013 - Mar 2015 (almost 2 years)

Role: Consultant

Project Description:

The project has been implemented in a Public Private Partnership (PPP) mode with Tata Consultancy Services, selected through a public competitive procurement process. Under this program, the sovereign and fiduciary functions like verification, granting and issuing of passport have been retained by MEA. The ownership and strategic control of the

core assets including data/information is with MEA.

Passport Seva enables simple, efficient and transparent processes for delivery of passport and related services. Apart from creating a countrywide networked environment for Government staff, it integrates with the State Police for physical verification of applicant's credentials and with India Post for delivery of passports.

Services Offered

- Apply or renewal for passport.
- Tracking of passport application.
- Grievance/feedback services for passport.
- Tracking of grievance services.
- Locate passport seva kendras.
- Fee Calculation.
- Tatkaal/normal appointment availability information.
- Downloading or printing of application form. Etc.

Responsibilities:

Working as a back-end developer and performed these responsibility during my tenure on this project:

- Worked as a programmer and worked on token management, Appointment scheduling module.
- SLA monitoring and auditing.
- Preparing bug list and shared across the team.
- Analysis issues locked by offline or online user and work

around for solution

Participate in 3rd party audit.

Technologies:

Java/Java EE, OOPS, Multithreading, Struts2, Hibernate, Ant as a build tool, DB2, WAS, Jenkins, JUnit, Nagios, LDAP, Linux

1. Company: CDAC, Mumbai

Duration: Sep 2010 - Apr 2013 (over 2 years)

Role: Sr Technical Associate

Project Description:

The project has been implemented in a Public Private Partnership (PPP) mode with Tata Consultancy Services, selected through a public competitive procurement process. Under this program, the sovereign and fiduciary functions like verification, granting and issuing of passport have been retained by MEA. The ownership and strategic control of the core assets including data/information is with MEA.

Passport Seva enables simple, efficient and transparent processes for delivery of passport and related services. Apart from creating a countrywide networked environment for Government staff, it integrates with the State Police for physical verification of applicant's credentials and with India Post for delivery of passports.

Services Offered

- Apply or renewal for passport.
- Tracking of passport application.
- Grievance/feedback services for passport.
- Tracking of grievance services.
- Locate passport seva kendras.
- Fee Calculation.
- Tatkaal/normal appointment availability information.
- Downloading or printing of application form. Etc.

Responsibilities:

- Worked as a programmer and worked on token management, Appointment scheduling module.
- SLA monitoring and auditing.
- Preparing bug list and shared across the team.
- Analysis issues locked by offline or online user and work around for solution
- Participate in 3rd party audit.

Technologies:

Java/Java EE, OOPS, Multithreading, Struts2, Hibernate, Ant as a build tool, DB2, WAS, Jenkins, JUnit, Nagios, LDAP, Linux.